A Guide to the George Weedon Papers, 1776-1789
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
George Weedon Papers, 1776-1789
The Library of Virginia
22954a
43 leaves, negative photostats
George Weedon
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Photostats purchased, 1949, from the Chicago Historical Society, Chicago, Illinois.
Biographical Information
George Weedon was born in late 1734 in Westmoreland County, Virginia. Weedon was appointed an ensign in the Virginia militia during the French and Indian War and rose to the rank of lieutenant in 1757 and to the rank of captain lieutenant in 1762. After the war, he moved to Fredericksburg, Virginia, and married Catharine Gordon (d. 1797). He operated a tavern in Fredericksburg. Weedon was appointed a lieutenant colonel in the 3rd Virginia Regiment in January 1776 and received a commission in the continental army 13 February 1776. He was promoted to colonel in June 1776. In August 1776, he and his troops joined the continental army in New York. Appointed a brigadier general 21 February 1777, Weedon served with the army until retiring because of a dispute in rank and for his health. He was recalled to active duty in 1780 to organize and command troops in Virginia. He served at the siege of Yorktown, Virginia. After the war, Weedon returned to Fredericksburg and operated his tavern. Active in local politics, he served on Fredericksburg's council and as its mayor. Weedon died 23 December 1793 in Fredericksburg.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1776-1789, from General George Weedon (1734-1793) of Fredericksburg, Virginia, and of the Continental army to John Page (1744-1808) of Gloucester County, Virginia, and president of the council discussing the condition of the Continental Army, the evacuation of New York, American and British military maneuvers in New York and Canada, the American victories and Trenton and Princeton, New Jersey, possible British movements against Virginia, the battles of Brandywine and Germantown, the American victory at Saratoga, New York, camp life at Valley Forge and skirmishes between American and British forces in southeastern Pennsylvania, Maryland troops, Weedon's service in and departure from the Continental Army, General George Washington (1732-1799), General Horatio Gates (1728-1806), British Generals John Burgoyne (1722-1792) and William Howe (1729-1814), request for financial assistance for the son of General Hugh Mercer (ca. 1725-1777), and an anecdote about General William Alexander, Lord Stirling (1726-1783).
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
Originals are located at the Chicago Historical Society, Chicago, Illinois.
Contents List
- Letter, 20 September 1776, discussing the condition of the army, the evacuation of New York City, and General George Washington's anger at the army's poor performance.
- Letter, 10 October 1776, containing information on British maneuvers in Canada and upper New York.
- Letter, 26 October 1776, detailing British and American maneuvers around New York.
- Letter, 29 December 1776, informing Page of the American victory at Trenton, New Jersey.
- Letter, 6 January 1777, describing the American victories at Trenton and Princeton, New Jersey, and discussing American strategy.
- Letter, 15 April 1777, discussing Washington, General Horatio Gates (1728-1806), and Weedon's leave in Virginia.
- Letter, 31 May 1777, discussing Washington and the condition of the army.
- Letter, 22 August 1777, concerning possible British movements against Virginia, camp life, and British and American maneuvers in upper New York.
- Report, 11 September 1777, on the battle of Brandywine in Pennsylvania including a sketched map.
- Letter, 4 October 1777, containing news about the battle of Brandywine and fighting at Germantown, Pennsylvania, as well as speculation on the British army under John Burgoyne (1722-1792) in New York.
- Letter, 8 October 1777, concerning Germantown and Burgoyne.
- Letter, 15 October 1777, containing news on the American victory at the battle of Saratoga in upper New York.
- Letter, 15 October 1777, containing news on the American victory at the battle of Saratoga in upper New York, including a copy of letter from Committee of city of Albany to President, Committee of Safety.
- Letter, 31 October 1777, containing an account of troops and supplies surrendered by Burgoyne at Saratoga.
- Letter, 17 December 1777, discussing British general William Howe (1729-1814), camp life at Valley Forge, Pennsylvania, and skirmishing outside Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
- Letter, 25 January 1778, discussing the skirmishes between American and British troops near Valley Forge
- Letter, 31 March 1778, written from Fredericksburg, Virginia, discussing the movement of Maryland troops through the area to join the Continental Army.
- Letter, 12 April 1779, discussing Weedon's departure from the army and general news on events.
- Letter, 23 July 1789, asking for financial help for the son of General Hugh Mercer (ca. 1725-1777), and reminiscencing about his revolutionary service, including an anecdote about William Alexander, Lord Stirling (1726-1783).